"Turmeric Supplements and Liver Toxicity"
Liver injury associated
with turmeric:
Ten cases from the Drug-Induced
Liver Injury Network
in the United States,
and there are others too,
including three cases
reported in Australia
and a series reported to
the Italian Ministry of Health.
Is turmeric really
a new hepatotoxic substance?
First of all, regardless of what
the titles of the papers say,
these cases appear to be from
turmeric extract supplements,
rather than turmeric the spice.
It's like green tea
and green tea extract pills.
Brewed green tea appears
to be completely safe
for the liver,
but give people green
tea extract supplements,
and the livers of as many as
1 in 17 people becomes inflamed.
So, we should consume
our green tea in beverage form,
not pill form,
and similarly,
our turmeric in spice form
at culinary doses,
not capsules,
unless they contain
just a single ingredient:
whole spice turmeric,
not curcumin,
not an extract,
no other ingredients.
While turmeric extract
supplements
have a relatively safe
side-effect profile
even at high doses,
there is an increasing number
of case reports linking them
to liver injury,
especially when combined
with agents such as piperine,
a compound found
in black pepper.
As we've covered before,
compounds like piperine
are added to turmeric
to enhance the
bioavailability of curcumin,
potentially contributing
to its toxicity,
as one reason curcumin may be so
safe is that it is poorly absorbed.
As we have cautioned before,
piperine blocks
liver detox enzymes
that can make some substances
like curcumin more potent.
And turmeric curcumin
supplement formulations
with high bioavailability,
such as nanoformulations
or those with added piperine,
have been less investigated.
There is a mistaken assumption
that if a little is good,
then more must be better.
We'd never make
that assumption for drugs,
so why is it made
for supplements?
In this case, more does not
necessarily mean better.
A review of nearly a hundred
randomized controlled trials
of turmeric or
curcumin supplements
for nonalcoholic
fatty liver disease
found that they successfully
calmed liver inflammation.
And guess
which worked better?
Low-dose supplements
worked about 10 times better
than high-dose ones.
There are caveats, though,
even for whole food turmeric.
As Dr. Greger
has covered before,
people who have a tendency
to form kidney stones
should be careful
due to turmeric's relatively
high oxalate content.
During a routine exam,
this unfortunate man
was found
to have kidney failure
due to his chronic
turmeric intake,
which led
to oxalate nephropathy,
where oxalate crystalizes
in our kidneys.
That was after taking
only 2 grams
or 2/3 of a teaspoon
of turmeric every day
for two years.
And taking
a few spoonfuls a day
of the actual spice itself
may indeed be enough
to cause liver injury,
as happened
to this pregnant woman.
Dr. Greger recommends
only a quarter teaspoon a day
in his Daily Dozen.
There's also been concern
about lead contamination
of the whole food spice.
Lead chromate
has been used
to make turmeric appear
more yellow in Bangladesh,
where much of turmeric sold in
the United States is imported from,
leading to multiple recalls.
The wonderful news is
food safety policies can work!
Since the original paper
of lead chromate contamination
in turmeric from Bangladesh,
the portion
of market turmeric samples
with detectable lead
went from about 50 percent
to zero.
Unfortunately, there is still
more work to be done, though.
In four South Asian countries
where more than 80 percent
of the world's turmeric
is produced,
14 percent of samples had
detectable lead above 2 ug/g.
For context,
this is 20 times higher
than the U.S. Food
and Drug Administration's
maximum allowable level
for lead in candy.
And some stores
sold turmeric
containing much higher levels
of lead
that would result
in projected blood lead levels
in children up to
10 times higher
than the U.S. Centers
for Disease Control's
threshold for concern.
This is a reminder that just
because something is natural
doesn't mean
it can't cause harm.
Turmeric dietary supplements
are big business,
estimated to account
for $69 million in sales
in the United States alone.
Though its popularity does help
put the recent spate
of liver toxicity
cases in context.
More than 10 million people
in the United States
take turmeric
or curcumin supplements.
So, that would be like
one case in a million.
Some people may just be more
susceptible genetically—
7 of the 10 patients
in this case series
had a genetic variant
that's relatively rare
in the general population.
Still, it's safer for
everyone to use the real thing
and not some extract
in some supplement.
And please don't let anyone
inject turmeric or curcumin
into your veins.